Guide to the Memory Project Oral History collection, 2009-2016 | 民间记忆计划口述史 RL.10171
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Hubei province | 湖北省, 2012-2016
  - Diaoyutai Village | 随州市随县殷店镇钓鱼台村, 2010-2016
    - Zhu Shunlian | 朱顺莲, 2011
      Zhu Shunlian (b. 1937) was born in Zhushan County, Shiyan City, Hubei Province, and moved to Diaoyutai Village (Yindian Town, Suizhou City, Hubei Province) in 1988. Her husband was once the production team leader. In this interview, Zhu recalls that she and her husband worked at Zhushan mine and ate at the People's Commune canteen in 1959. The food available in the canteen and households included buckwheat, corn flour, grass root, rice chaff, tree leaves, chingma abutilon seed and wild walnut, as well as a mixture made of soy milk, pumpkin leaves, string bean leaves, potato leaves and wild plants. Zhu also remembers that some people from Sichuan escaped to Hubei because of the famine.
      朱顺莲（1937年生）出生于湖北省十堰市竹山县, 1988年搬迁到湖北省随州市殷店镇钓鱼台村。朱老人的丈夫年轻时当过生产队长。在这段口述中, 朱老人讲述了自己和丈夫59年跟随生产队在竹山矿场劳动和吃食堂的故事。当地人在集体食堂和家里吃花荞、苞谷面、草头木根、花米糠、桐柏树叶子、茼麻籽和野核桃, 以及在家用黄豆豆浆、南瓜叶子、四季豆叶子、土豆叶子、野菜打锅渣吃。另外, 朱老人还回忆有四川人逃荒到湖北。
    - Xia Changying | 夏常英, 2012
      Xia Changying (b. 1946) is a resident of Diaoyutai Village, Yindian Town, Suizhou City, Hubei Province. Her father died when she was eight, and her mother died when she was thirteen. Since 1959 he and her four sisters suffered from constipation because of eating chaff. They also ate water elm bark and water grass. Zijin Mountain was called 'Mountain of the Dead' because many people, who worked on mines there for constructing blast furnace, died there. In 1964, when the Four Cleanups began, Xia married to a man in Minyue production team. She and the local people participated in reservoir construction during the daytime, and in criticizing those who hadn't cleaned up their reactionary elements at night. She specifically mentioned how Li, who was selected as the president of poor peasant association, lied to criticize other people.
      夏常英（1946年生）是湖北省随州市殷店镇钓鱼台村村民, 8岁时父亲去世, 13岁时母亲去世。夏老人家里姐妹五人, 1959年开始吃糠导致排便困难, 另外还吃榔树皮和水草。当地人把紫金山叫做'死人山'，因为为了炼钢铁去那里挖矿的人很多都死在那里。四清运动开始的1964年, 夏常英嫁到民跃大队。白天参加水库建设, 晚上开会批斗'四不清'。她特别提到队里的李＊＊被工作组选为贫协主席, 开会时说假话批斗'四不清'。
    - He Gaoshan | 何高山, 2013
      He Gaoshan (b. 1936) is a resident of Diaoyutai Village, Hubei Province. In this interview, He recalls his difficult life as well as his experience during the Land Reform, the Great Leap Forward and the Great Famine. His parents passed away when he was young, and all of his brothers also died of starvation due to poverty. His original family name was Yu, but it was changed to He after he was sold to the He family by his uncle and left his hometown. However, his life was still very difficult. During the Great Famine, He saw the wife of a production team leader who was working outside hung herself because of hunger.
      何高山1936年出生, 是湖北省随州市随县殷店镇钓鱼台村村民。在这段口述中, 何老人回忆了自己辛酸的一生以及土改、大跃进、大饥荒时的情况。何老人从小父母双亡, 兄弟也都因为贫穷饿死了。他原本姓余, 后来被舅舅卖给了何家, 从此离开老家, 但生活仍十分艰苦。大饥荒期间, 何老人看见一个队长出工干活, 老婆在家饿得吊死。
    - Chen Xinmin | 陈新民, 2012
      Chen Xinmin (b.1943) is a resident of Diaoyutai Village, Yindian Town, Suizhou City, Hubei Province. The Great Famine, according to him, was because the central government in 1959 encouraged people to 'tighten their belts' in order to pay off the debt to Soviet Union, the local cadres exaggerated about the grain production for their political achievements, and they made unfair allocation of the grain. Chen talks about how several fellow villagers starved to death, including the controversy over whether Ma Zhengyi died of starvation or of overeating. Chen described in detail about the Four Cleanups movement based on his own experience of being criticized and writing self criticism. Chen was found as 'clean' by the movement, so he became a cadre in the production team at the beginning of the Cultural Revolution. In 1968-1969, he was the director of the Revolution Committee. Chen says that the Revolution Committee was in charge of any chaotic situation caused by beating, smashing, and looting, and his village maintained peaceful social order during the Cultural Revolution.
      陈新民（1943年生）是湖北省随州市殷店镇钓鱼台村村民。他的口述涉及大饥荒、四清运动和文革三个主题。关于大饥荒, 他解释原因是1959年中央政府提出百姓'把肚子勒一下'偿还苏联债务, 部分基层干部为了政绩虚报粮食产量, 而且对于本地存储的粮食管理分配有问题。陈老人还讲述了当地几位村民饿死的情况, 包括关于马正义是饿死还是涨死的争议。关于四清运动, 陈老人结合自己受生产队开会批斗、写检讨的经历, 详细讲述了运动发展的情况。因为运动中没有被查出问题, 文革开始后陈老人一直在生产队担任干部, 特别是1968－1969年间担任革委会主任。陈老人讲述革命委员会专门管理文革期间打砸抢的混乱局面, 他所在的乡没有出现乱局。
    - Liu Zhengying | 刘正英, 2012
      Liu Zhengying (b. 1945) is a resident of Diaoyutai Village, Yindian Town, Suizhou City, Hubei Province. Liu's mother died of disease when she was less than one year old, and her father raised her while remained single. This interview was co-completed by Zhang Mengqi and Liu's grandson, Zou Xue song, who was a first-year middle school student. In this interview, Liu recounts in detail how she cooked wild herbs, tree bark, plant leaves, and chaff to survive famine in 1959, and how she made sweets by barley sugar and peanuts in 1961. In 1959, when the famine was most serious, Liu went to the local leaders' conference location to stole food, which were cooked for the leaders, and then distribute them to her family and neighbors. This starving situation did not change until 1962, when People's Commune finished.
      刘正英（1945年生）是湖北省随州市殷店镇钓鱼台村村民。刘老人的母亲生下她不到一年就因病去世, 父亲独自把她抚养成人。该采访由章梦奇和被采访人的孙子——初一学生邹雪松——共同完成。在这段口述中, 刘老人详细介绍了1959年饥饿时期用于果腹的野草、树皮、植物叶子、糠等的烹饪方法, 以及1961年左右自己用大麦做糖、跟花生一起做成糖果吃的经历。1959年最为饥饿的时候, 刘老人到干部们开会吃饭的地点偷饭, 带回家给家人和邻居吃。这种饥饿的状况直到1962年人民公社食堂结束, 才稍有改变。
    - Liu Shunfang | 刘顺芳, 2010
      Liu Shunfang (b.1948) is a resident of Diaoyutai Village, Yindian Town, Suizhou City, Hubei Province. She is one of the few villagers who is educated, and has three sisters. In this interview, Liu talks about her father with poor health went to build railroad in order to save food for the family. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      刘顺芳（1948年生）是湖北省随州市殷店镇钓鱼台村村民。她是少数受过教育的村民之一, 并有三个姐妹。在这段口述中, 刘老人讲述了身体不好的父亲在饥荒期间为给家里省下口粮去修铁路的经历。
    - Gong Zhiqing | 宫志清, 2012
      Gong Zhiqing (b. 1941) is a resident of Diaoyutai Village, Hubei Province. In this interview, Gong talks about the Great Famine. According to Gong, the cause of the famine was China's paying off the foreign debt. Gong thinks there was nothing wrong with the policies made by the higher-level government, but due to the negligence of and exaggerated harvest reports made by the local cadres, the villagers suffered a lot from the famine. Gong also talks about the life in 1959 when building the Zijin Mountain reservoir and the causes of death for those who died of starvation during that time. According to Gong, over one hundred people from Minyue Brigade (namely, Diaoyutai Village) starved to death. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      宫志清1941年出生, 是湖北省随州市殷店镇钓鱼台村村民。在这段口述中, 宫老人回忆了大饥荒时期的情况。据宫老人讲述, 当时挨饿的原因是国家还外债。宫老人认为, 上级的政策并没问题, 但当地村干部不作为, 虚报收成, 导致村民受灾挨饿, 自己却有粮食吃。宫老人还讲述了1959年去紫金山修水库的生活, 以及当年因饥饿去世的村民的死亡原因。宫老人回忆说, 当时整个民跃大队（即钓鱼台村）饿死超过一百人。
    - Li Xiaodong | 李小东, 2012
    - Wang Yifa | 王义发, 2010-2012
      Wang Yifa (b. 1945) is a resident of Diaoyutai Village, Yindian Town, Suizhou City, Hubei Province. In 1958, Wang was a work-study student; he pastured cattles for the production team. Then people ate for free in the People's Commune Canteen, but soon the commune canteen ran out of food except chaff. Wang went to Zijin Mountain to join the railway construction project to feed himself. The local production team blew up the team's population to gain more relief grain. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      王义发（1945年生）是湖北省随州市殷店镇钓鱼台村村民, 1958年13岁的王老人一边上学一边给生产队放牛挣工分。公社食堂可以免费吃饭, 但后期食堂无粮只能吃糠, 王老人跑去紫金山参加修铁路才吃饱饭。当地生产队为了让群众吃饱饭, 虚报人数领取补助粮。
    - Wang Wenyu | 王文玉, 2010
      Wang Wenyu (b. 1941) is a resident of Diaoyutai Village, Yindian Town, Suizhou City, Hubei Province. He worked for railroad and dam construction as a teenager. In this interview, Wang recalls the hardships on the construction site and in his family during the Great Famine (or what he calls 'the transitional period'). The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      王文玉（1941年生）是湖北省随州市殷店镇钓鱼台村村民, 十几岁就参加了铁路和水利修建工作。在这段口述中, 王老人回忆了大饥荒期间（或他口中的'生活过渡'）工地上和家里艰难的情形。
    - Yang Houxin | 杨厚新, 2010
      Yang Houxin (b. 1948) is a resident of Diaoyutai Village, Yindian Town, Suizhou City, Hubei Province. His father died before his birth, he lived with his mother and an older sister, who got married during the Great Famine. Yang and his mother fed on tree bark and wild herbs. This difficult situation did not change until the second half of 1961.
      杨厚新（1948年生）是湖北省随州市殷店镇钓鱼台村村民。杨老人出生之前父亲就已经去世, 他与母亲和一个姐姐相依为命。大饥荒时期姐姐出嫁, 杨老人与母亲吃树皮、野菜为生。这种状况直到1961年下半年才开始得到缓解。
    - Yao Guangxue | 姚光学, 2010
      Yao Guangxue (b. 1945) is a resident of Diaoyutai Village, Yindian Town, Suizhou City, Hubei Province, and lives in an old house with a hundred years of history. In this interview, Yao talks about what kind of food (tree bark, wild plants, etc.) his family ate and how they ate them to survive the Great Famine. He particularly remembers a Production Team leader called Dai Mingshan, who often peaked into their house when they were eating. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      姚光学（1945年生）是湖北省随州市殷店镇钓鱼台村村民, 现居住在一间百年老屋里。 在这段口述中, 姚老人回忆了他的家人为了在大饥荒中生存下来吃了什么（树皮, 野草等），怎么吃的。他尤其记得一个时常偷看他们家吃饭的生产队长, 戴明山。
    - Qiu Jiafa | 邱家发, 2010
      Qiu Jiafa (b.1940) is a resident of Diaoyutai Village, Yindian Town, Suizhou City, Hubei Province. During the Great Famine, Qiu was in middle school and his teachers led students to find oak tree seed and bark, vitex leaves and Chinese scholar tree flowers for food. All members of the production team had to participate in building the reservoir and a meal provided by the People's Commune Canteen included only two liang of rice and boiled water grass. Qiu's father starved to death in 1959. Qiu believes that the Great Famine happened partly because the cadres much exaggerated the grain production to gain political achievements, and partly because the cadres stole some grain given by the government. Commune members of the production team dared not report because they were afraid of the vengency from the cadres.
      邱家发（1940年生）是湖北省随州市殷店镇钓鱼台村村民。大饥荒时期邱老人在上中学, 因为饥饿学校老师组织学生们去山里打橡籽、挖橡树皮、黄荆树叶和槐树花吃。全生产队都参与修水库, 每顿饭在集体食堂吃的是二两米和煮水草。邱老人的父亲1959年被饿死。老人认为饥荒的原因一是干部为了自己的政绩向上虚报产量, 二是基层干部贪污皇粮之外的'义粮'。这些情况社员们不敢向上告发是因为害怕基层干部的打击报复。
    - Shu Jiaqing | 蜀家清, 2012
      Shu Jiaqing (b. 1934) is a resident of Diaoyutai Village, Yindian Town, Suizhou City, Hubei Province, and now lives alone in a shabby house. Her husband, the company commander in Minyue Production Team, passed away more than a decade ago. In this interview, Shu recalls the day when her neighbor He Kaiguo hung himself to death due to starvation during the Great Famine. She also describes the experience of confiscation of family possessions during the Four Cleanups Movement. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      蜀家清（1934年生）是湖北省随州市殷店镇钓鱼台村村民, 现在一个人住在简陋的小屋里。她的老伴（民跃大队的连长）十多年前去世了。在这段口述中, 蜀老人回忆了大饥荒期间她的邻居何开国因为饥饿上吊自杀当天的情况。随后她还描述了四清运动中一家人被抄家的经历。
    - Wan Qisheng | 万启升, 2010
      Wan Qisheng (b.1935) is a resident of Diaoyutai Village, Yindian Town, Suizhou City, Hubei Province, and both his parents died when he was 13. Wan talks about eating water elm bark, peanut leaves, wild grass, water grass and bran during the Great Famine. Wan believes the nation had a shortage of grain reservation at this time because a lot of grain were given to the Soviet Union, and the starvation among the members of the production team was because the cadres exaggerated the grain production and collected all the grain from the farmers.
      万启升（1935年生）是湖北省随州市殷店镇钓鱼台村村民, 13岁时父母双亡。万老人回忆了自己大饥荒时期吃榔树皮、花生叶子、野草、水草、糠果腹的经历。万老人认为大饥荒时期国家没有粮食是因为粮食都给了苏联, 当地生产队社员饿死是因为生产队干部虚报产量, 把粮食都从农民手中收走。
    - Jiang Wangying | 姜旺英, 2012
      Jiang Wangying (b.1931) is a resident of Diaoyutai Village, Yindian Town, Suizhou City, Hubei Province. She had her younger son in 1959. In this oral history, Jiang recalls Ma Dazhu, who starved to death while building railroad in Zijin Mountain. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      姜旺英（1931年生）是湖北省随州市殷店镇钓鱼台村村民。她在1959年生下了小儿子。在这段口述中, 姜老人回忆了在紫金山修铁路时被饿死的马大柱。
    - Ma Guangxue | 马光学, 2012
      Ma Guangxue (b.1937) is a resident of Diaoyutai Village, Yindian Town, Suizhou City, Hubei Province. In 1959 when local people were most starving, Ma worked in a silkworm farm, where he was able to eat silkworm pupas to get nutrition. Like Chen Xinmin, Ma talks about how several fellow villagers starved to death, including the controversy over whether Ma Zhengyi died of starvation or of overeating. Before the Four Cleanups, Ma was in charge of recording work points of the production team members. During the Four Cleanups, leaders who misbehaved were criticized as those who hadn't cleaned up the reactionary elements. The criticism was much harsher during the Cultural revolution. Ma also briefly talks about the administration system of the production team. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      马光学（1937年生）是湖北省随州市殷店镇钓鱼台村村民。马老人的口述涉及大饥荒、四清运动和文革三个主题。1959年最饥饿的时候, 马老人在外地的蚕场工作, 通过吃蚕蛾儿补充营养。与陈新民老人一样, 马老人也讲述了村里几位村民饿死的情况, 包括关于马正义是饿死还是涨死的争论。四清运动之前, 马老人曾经担任生产队的记分员。关于四清运动, 他解释做事不正当、不清楚的干部就是受到批判的'四不清'，文革期间对干部的批斗更加严厉。另外, 马老人还简要介绍了生产队的管理体系构成
    - Ma Guangyun | 马光云, 2012
      Ma Guangyun(b.1939) is a resident of Diaoyutai Village, Hubei Province. He recalls that a lot of people died of starvation in 1959. People even ate all the tree leaves and barks. They also ate cotton leaves and soy bean leaves, almost anything they could find. He went to work at railroad construction but was still hungry all the time. He was told that the shortage of food was because the country needed to pay back debts owed to the Soviet Union. His village suffered the most because the village party secretary refused help. They also went to build Zijinshan reservoir. They had to work on empty stomach. Many people starved to death.
      马光云（1939年生）是湖北省随州市随县殷店镇钓鱼台村村民。他记得1959年饿死了很多人, 人们把树叶和树皮都吃光了。还吃棉花叶子、黄豆叶子, 找到什么吃什么。他去修铁路, 也吃不饱。他听说粮食短缺是因为要还苏联的债。 他的村子饿死的人多是因为他们的书记拒绝了上面的供应。他们去修紫金山水库时, 肚子饿仍然要干活, 饿死了很多人。
    - Ma Dagui | 马大贵, 2012
      Ma Dagui(b.1934) is a resident of Diaoyutai Village, Hubei Province. He's single. He was given two rooms previously owned by a landlord during the Land Reform. He repeatedly says that the Great Famine was because of the difficulties China experienced. He ate things that tasted horrible. During the Cultural Revolution, he was appointed the deputy production team leader.
      马大贵（1934年生）是湖北省随州市随县殷店镇钓鱼台村村民。他是个单身汉, 土改时分到了地主家的两间屋。他反复强调饥荒是因为国家有困难。他吃过非常难吃的东西。文革期间他被任命为副队长。
    - Zhang Mingying | 张明英, 2012
      Zhang Mingying (b. 1947) is a resident of Diaoyutai Village, Yindian Town, Suizhou City, Hubei Province. She is the daughter-in-law of the other interviewee, Yu Xiantang. Zhang recalls that people ate chaff, tree leaves, cotton leaves, bean and peanut leaves, and water grass. Many people died in Zijin Mountain, where people worked on mines for constructing blast furnace, so the Mountain was later called 'Mountain of the Dead.' In 1959, people who stole things were humiliated in a parade around the local villages while hitting a gong by himself. Those who held disagreements against 'the transitional period' were convicted for counterrevolutionary. Zhang's younger sister was named Siqing (meaning Four Cleanups), because she was born in 1964 when the campaign started. Zhang also talks about how people were beaten at the criticizing meetings during the cultural revolution.
      张明英（1947年生）是湖北省随州市殷店镇钓鱼台村村民, 是另一位受访者余先堂的儿媳妇。张老人回忆了1959年当地人吃糠、树叶子, 棉花叶子、黄豆叶子、花生叶子和水草等的情况。很多人饿死在去修水库的路上和挖矿的紫金山, 所以紫金山被称为'死人山'。1959年偷了东西的人要敲锣游乡, 对'粮食过渡'时期有不同意见的人要被打成反革命。张老人的妹妹名叫四清, 因为是四清运动开始的1964年出生。另外张老人还回忆了文革期间批斗会打人的情况。
    - Zhu Guangjian | 朱广建, 2010-2012
      Zhu Guangjian (b. 1941) is a resident of Diaoyutai Village, Yindian Town, Suizhou City, Hubei Province. Zhu believes that the grain shortage was because China needed to pay debt to the Soviet Union with grain. But later in the interview, he also talks about the boasting and exaggeration of grain production during 'the transitional period'. Since 1958 people could eat in the People's Commune Canteen for free. Soon the commune canteen failed to feed the people, who began to eat wild herbs, tree barks, corn leaves, water grass and chaff. In 1959 Zhu participated in the construction of Handan Railway because he could have more food there. Zhu recalls that most fellow villagers died of starvation were adults. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      朱广建（1941年生）是湖北省随州市殷店镇钓鱼台村村民。朱老人认为粮食缺少的的原因是国家需要集中粮食给苏联还账, 在之后的采访中他也提到了'粮食过渡'时期的浮夸风。1958年免费吃食堂, 后来食堂吃不饱人们开始吃野菜、榔树皮、青桐树皮、棉花叶子、水草和糠的情况。1959年朱老人辍学参加汉丹铁路建设, 因为能够吃得多一些。另外, 老人还回忆村里饿死的大多是成年人。
    - Zhou Chengyou | 周呈友, 2012
      Zhou Chengyou (b. 1941) is a resident of Diaoyutai Village, Yindian Town, Suizhou City, Hubei Province. He was the leader of No. 3 production team for 20 years since he was in his twenties. Zhou believes that 'the transitional period' of grains (the Great Famine) was because China had to pay debts to foreign countries. He recalls a few people who starved to death in different production teams. Zhou described in detail about the procedure of struggle sessions during the Four Cleanups, how he was criticized as he hadn't cleaned up some reactionary elements. He argues that the Four Cleanups movement was good at the beginning, but was overdone as it developed. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      周呈友（1941年生）是湖北省随州市殷店镇钓鱼台村村民, 从二十多岁起担任第三生产队队长二十余年。周老人认为粮食过渡时期(大饥荒)的产生是因为要偿还外国债务, 另外他还回忆了各个生产队被饿死的人的情况。关于四清运动, 周老人详细讲述了批斗会的流程, 以及他本人作为'四不清'受到批斗的经历。他认为四清运动开始很好, 后来发展过火了。
    - Peng Kaiying | 彭开英, 2010
      Peng Kaiying (b.1926) was born in Diaoyutai Village, Yindian Town, Suizhou City, Hubei Province. She worked on dam construction in Tianjiawan during the Great Famine. In this interview, Peng talks about people in her production team who starved to death at that time. She also recalls how women searched for food while building the dam. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      彭开英1926年出生于湖北省随州市殷店镇钓鱼台村. 大饥荒期间她曾在田家湾修水库。在这段口述中, 彭老人说起那时在她的生产队里饿死的人。她也回忆了修水库的妇女们是如何寻找食物的。
  - Xiahe Village | 随州市万店镇下河村中湾, 2016
    Xiahe Village is located in Sui County, Suizhou City, Hubei Province. Interviews in this sub-series were conducted and filmed by Zhang Mengqi.
    下河村位于湖北省随州市随县殷店镇。村民的录像采访人是章梦奇。
    - He Jinxiu | 何锦绣, 2016
  - Yanzi River Town | 随州市岩子河乡, 2016
    Yanzi River Town is located in Sui County, Suizhou City, Hubei Province. Interviews in this sub-series were conducted and filmed by Zhang Mengqi.
    岩子河乡位于湖北省随州市随县殷店镇。村民的录像采访人是章梦奇。
    - Zhang Xiufeng | 章秀峰, 2016
- Hunan province | 湖南省, 2009-2016
  - Heiqi Village | 永州市东安县大庙口镇黑漆村, 2016
    Heiqi Village is located in Dongan County, Yangzhou City, Hunan Province. Interviews in this sub-series were conducted and filmed by Luo Bing.
    黑漆村位于湖南省永州市东安县大庙口镇。村民的录像采访人是张苹。
    - Zhu Xiaoqin | 朱晓琴, 2016
    - Zhang Chaomin | 张朝珉, 2016
      Zhang Chaomin (b. 1933) is a resident of Heiqi Village, Damiaokou Town, Dong'an County, Hunan Province. He is the interviewer's father. In this interview, Zhang talks about his family history: the death of his mother, the working experience during his childhood, and his two previous marriages. He also recalls how he guided the troops of the Liberation Army during the bandit suppressions. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      张朝珉出生于1933年，是湖南省永州东安县大庙口村黑漆村的村民。他是采访人的父亲。在这段口述中，张老人讲述了家族历史、他母亲的死、童年帮工、他的前两段婚姻选择以及他剿匪带路的经历。
    - Fan Chunyan | 范春燕, 2016
      Fan Chunyan (b. 1939) is a resident of Heiqi Village, Damiaokou Town, Dong'an County, Hunan Province. She is the interviewer's mother. In this interview, Fan recalls about her life, her childhood experiences, her father's way of living and how most members in the Fan family died during the Land Reform. She also recalls life in the steel mill while constructing blast furnace and life in the countryside when she and her husband were sent down there because he was labeled as a rightist. She also talks about her giving birth, etc. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      范春燕出生于1939年，是湖南省东安县大庙口镇黑漆村的村民。她也是采访人的母亲。在这段口述中，范老人回忆了自己的一生：范家在土改中的灭族之难、父亲的存世之道、童年遭遇、大炼钢铁的钢厂生活、受丈夫右派连累的农村生活、她的生育故事等。
    - Zhang Wenbin | 张文斌, 2016
      Zhang Wenbin (b.1933) is a resident of Heiqi Village, Damiaokou Town, Dong'an County, Hunan Province. In this interview, Zhang talks about his bitter days after the Liberation, and commented on the policy mistakes during the People's Commue canteen time and the Cultural Revolution. Because he was born in a landlord family, he quitted school after the Liberation. At 18 years old, he became a major labor force and had to do all kinds of work. The entire family relied on him. It only got better after collectivization in 1955. The transcript of this interview has been translated into English.
      张文斌1933年出生， 是湖南省永州东安县大庙口村黑漆村的村民。在这段口述中，张老人讲述了解放后自己过的苦日子，同时评论了吃食堂和文革时得政策失误等。因为出生在地主家庭，解放后他就没继续读书。18岁就成了主要劳动力，一个人养家，什么都要做。直到1955年集体化后日子才好过一点。
    - Pen Jinhua | 彭金华, 2016
  - Taitai Village | 株洲市茶陵县潞水镇太台村, 2010
    Taitai Village is located in Chaling County, Zhuzhou City, Hunan Province. Interviews in this sub-series were conducted and filmed by Luo Bing.
    太台村位于湖南省株洲市茶陵县潞水镇。村民的录像采访人是罗兵。
    - Luo Taoxiang | 罗桃香, 2010
  - Gucheng Village | 株洲市茶陵县高陇镇古城村|, 2010
    Gucheng Village is located in Chaling County, Zhuzhou City, Hunan Province. Interviews in this sub-series were conducted and filmed by Luo Bing.
    古城村位于湖南省株洲市茶陵县潞水镇。村民的录像采访人是罗兵。
    - Luo Juying | 罗菊英, 2010
      Luo Juying (b. 1936) is a resident of Gucheng Village, Gaolong Town, Chaling County, Hunan Province. In this interview, Luo talks about how people ate wild herbs and chaff to survive the famine and how people, who were caught stealing vegetables from the people's commun canteen, were criticized at struggle sessions in 1960. Luo also talks about some villagers died because of the brutal treatment at struggle sessions and some who committed suicide because they were very scared of being criticized at struggle sessions during the Cultural Revolution.
      罗菊英（1936年生）是湖南省茶陵县高陇镇古城村村民。在这段口述中，罗老人讲述了1960年粮食匮乏、人们吃野草和糠等充饥，以及偷食堂的菜被抓后被开会批斗的情况。罗老人还讲述了文革期间有人被批斗致死、有人因为害怕挨批斗而自杀的情况。
  - Changxing Village | 株洲市茶陵县高陇镇长兴村, 2010-2012
    Changxing Village is located in Chaling County, Zhuzhou City, Hunan Province. Interviews in this sub-series were conducted and filmed by Luo Bing.
    长兴村位于湖南省株洲市茶陵县潞水镇。村民的录像采访人是罗兵。
    - Ge Haiqun | 葛海群, 2010
      Ge Haiqun (b. 1932) is a resident of Changxing Village, Gaolong Town, Chaling County, Hunan Province. In this interview, Ge talks about his experiences of constructing blast furnace and mining coal during the Great Leap Forward. In 1960, Ge returned home from the mine and then worked as the leader of the production team for almost a decade. Ge introduces in detail the standard of grading working points and the methods of cooking tree roots, grass roots, tree bark, wild herbs, as well as chaff to survive the famine. He believes that the cause of the famine was to pay debts to the Soviet Union. Ge also mentions the class struggles during the Great Famine.
      葛海群（1932年生）是湖南省茶陵县高陇镇长兴村村民。在这段口述中，葛老人讲述了大跃进时期大炼钢铁和在煤矿挖煤的经历。1960年代葛老人从煤矿回来，任生产队队长近十年，所以老人详细介绍了工分的评定方法。葛老人讲述了大饥荒时期烹饪树根、草根、树皮、野草、糠等，他认为大饥荒产生的原因是要给苏联还债。另外，葛老人还提到了大饥荒期间的阶级斗争情况。
    - Liang Lanfang | 梁芳兰, 2011